<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>tin_nqn (Posts about rust)</title><link>https://mgaitan.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://mgaitan.github.io/en/categories/rust.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2025 &lt;a href="mailto:gaitan@gmail.com"&gt;Martín Gaitán&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 02:41:05 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Expanding the Python universe with Rust</title><link>https://mgaitan.github.io/en/posts/expanding-the-python-universe-with-rust/</link><dc:creator>Martín Gaitán</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;My wife Natalia, among many &lt;a href="https://www.instagram.com/natinadibuja/"&gt;other talents she has&lt;/a&gt;, is a German-to-Spanish translator and, besides freelancing, works as a researcher and lecturer at the Universidad Nacional de Córdoba, Argentina.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably because foreign languages are almost as hard for me as dancing or singing (sorry to my colleagues who have had--and will have--to suffer through my spoken English), I have deep admiration for polyglots. Not for the mere ability to swap words or produce more vowel sounds, but for the power to know and feel different universes. That is what &lt;a href="https://borgestodoelanio.blogspot.com/2017/01/jorges-luis-borges-el-oficio-de-traducir.html"&gt;Jorge L. Borges was complaining about&lt;/a&gt; when someone mangled one of his tales with a translation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to dictionaries, languages are repertoires of synonyms, but they are not. Bilingual dictionaries make you believe that every word in one language can be replaced by another word in a different language. The mistake is ignoring that each language is a way of feeling the universe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I extrapolate that admiration for polyglotism--the art of widening your vital universe--to people who know many programming languages deeply. They bring ideas from one universe to the next, bursting bubbles, prejudices, blind spots. They propose new ways and limits, taking inspiration from here to create over there. Python would not exist without that kind of people. Long live those "Marco Polos" who connect universes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I'm ambitious (but not quite dedicated enough) to open a small window into the Rust universe, I compensate for my slowness and distraction with tools and shortcuts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a simple way to expand my Python universe with a "Marco Polo" who knows the Rust world and can open a window to that &lt;a href="https://crates.io/"&gt;other realm full of possibilities&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://mgaitan.github.io/en/posts/expanding-the-python-universe-with-rust/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (6 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bindings</category><category>maturin</category><category>pyo3</category><category>python</category><category>rust</category><guid>https://mgaitan.github.io/en/posts/expanding-the-python-universe-with-rust/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 17:15:23 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>